isometric exercise otherwise known as a
static hold has come up on top as the
best exercise to reduce blood pressure
even more so than other forms of
exercise like running lifting weights
and a number of others and much to my
happiness multiple people asked on the
last video going over the clinical data
why isometric exercise has such a
profound impact so what's so unique
about isometric exercise that gives it
this significant blood pressure lowering
effect
in brief isometric exercise is literally
just holding a stable position during an
exercise that means the muscle is not
shortening or lengthening like it would
if you were going through the rest of
the motion something about that position
leads to added benefit over exercise
that does undergo that lengthening and
shortening there are multiple reasons
exercise researchers compiled the
evidence for isometric exercise into a
scientific review and covered a number
of me mechanisms that could explain the
blood pressure lowering effect for one
isometric exercise may have an outsized
effect on a process called reactive
hyperemia in essence when the muscle is
stuck in one position the muscle fibers
and structure clamp down on the blood
vessels in that area this in effect
raises blood pressure quite dramatically
so unless I'm confused on which
direction I'm supposed to be arguing
there should be some way for that to
correct itself and better yet yet
plummet blood pressure lower than before
there is when the isometric hold is
released as in you move back out of the
isometric position the muscle relaxes
which also relaxes the blood vessels
returning blood pressure to where it was
before however we're not interested in
raising blood pressure and then bringing
it back down to where it was what good
does that do us fortunately that's not
entirely what happens the relaxation of
the muscle opens up the blood vessels
again and as blood rushes in it brings
with it oxygen nutrients and importantly
multiple factors like nitric oxide and
adenosine these bind the blood vessel
wall cells called smooth muscle cells
and encourage them to relax even further
this opens the blood vessels even wider
dropping blood pressure beyond the
initial point this sudden influx of
blood is called hyperia but the body
doesn't stop there because other factors
also play a role your body has receptors
built into specific sections of the
heart and even some blood vessels called
B receptors these bar receptors are
sensitive to changes in the blood
pressure if there's an increase in blood
pressure like when holding an isometric
position the bar receptors will send a
signal to the brain to reduce blood
pressure the brain does that through
direct communication with the heart and
the blood vessels via the nervous system
the brain encourages the heart rate to
fall and for blood vessels to stay open
in fact this review that we've been
gleaning this information from mentions
that there are studies where isometric
exercise reduce heart rate and blood
pressure 7 hours after the exercise
indicating a longstanding effect much of
the heart and blood pressure effects are
also confirmed including discussions of
the mechanisms in this systematic review
as well but let's go over one more such
explanation from why isometric exercise
provides the added benefits that it does
oh also there's some uh more nuances in
a step-by-step hand isometric protocol
that I created for the physionic
Insiders my premium research platform if
you're interested in more on the topic
including the protocol the link is in
the description surprisingly your
neurons inate or communicate with the
various cells that make up your blood
vessels if we zoom in we know that
neurons can influence the activity of
endothelial cells the cells responsible
for controlling the blood vessel size
remember the bigger the blood vessel the
lower the blood pressure generally
neurons can influence endothelial cells
to release more Vaso constriction or
vessel constriction factors or vessel
relaxing factors isometric exercise does
not seem to activate what's known as
sympathetic Drive sympathetic Drive is
the neurons encouraging the endothelial
cells to to release Vaso constriction
factors surprisingly isometric exercise
doesn't activate that pathway which
would typically be expected in fact
neurons themselves independent of
endothelial cells can release factors
like nitric oxide that directly bind and
cause relaxation of the blood vessels
called a parasympathetic Drive I do
think there's a lot to uncover yet but
at least we have some idea of what makes
isometric exercise unique and above all
so potent in reducing blood pressure if
you want to know the most effective
isometric exercise and how to do it and
more join me in this next video thanks
for watching
[Music]